Glass Bottle Blower's Association of the United States and Canada Records 5142
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Glass Bottle Blower's Association of the United States and Canada Records
1908- 1927
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Glass Bottle Blower's Association of the United States and Canada
5142
1.33 cubic feet
1.3 linear ft.
Minutes (administrative records).
Chiefly administrative correspondence; also minutes, clippings and a report on hearings on H.R. 16928.
2293700
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, February 25, 2014
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, November 01, 2016
Biographical / Historical
The Glass Bottle Blowers' Association of the United States and Canada (GBBA) was organized in 1868 as the Independent Druggist Ware Glass Blowers' League. It affiliated with the Knights of Labor in 1886 and withdrew from this affiliation in 1891 to become the United Green Glass Workers' Association of the United States and Canada, assuming its present name in 1895.
Scope and Contents
Chiefly administrative correspondence; also minutes, clippings and a report on hearings H.R. 16928.
The records include correspondence (1890-1915) (3 bound volumes of carabons and originals) containing letters from the Knights of Labor discussing possible amalgamation of the American Flint Glass Workers Union (AFGWU) and the Glass Bottle Blowers' Association (GBBA); letters from Denis A. Hayes (president, GBBA) regarding jurisdiction, machinery, wage and price guidelines; letter (1897) discussing amalgamation of GBBA with Prescription Bottle Department of AFGWU; protest of "Danbury Hatters Case" (Sherman Antitrust) (1910); jurisdictional dispute with AFGWU (1909); manufacturers beginning production of bottles during "summer shop" (1911); minutes and resolutions (1911) of committee to settle jurisdictional disputes between GBBA and AFGWU, etc. Major correspondents include D.A. Hayes (president, GBBA), Frank Morrison, Samuel Gompers, J.W. Rowe (president, AFGWU) and C.E. Voitle (president, AFGWU).
Aditional materials include (1 bound volume) proceedings/minutes of Conferences held between representatives of GBBA and AFGWU (1911); miscellaneous clippings (1900-1912); credential certificate for Harry Jenkins (1900); report of hearings on H.R. 16928 regarding regulation of storage of food products in District of Columbia, with statements by Harry Jenkins (1910); and souvenir booklet of GBBA "Golden Anniversary Convention" (1927).
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Bottle industry -- United States; Glassworkers; Danbury Hatters Case, 1910.; Labor unions -- Mergers -- United States; Glassworkers -- Labor unions -- United States -- Jurisdictional disputes; Labor unions -- Jurisdictional disputes -- United States; American Flint Glass Workers' Union; Glass Bottle Blowers Association of the United States and Canada; Knights of Labor; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924; Hayes, Denis A.; Jenkins, Harry; Powderly, Terence Vincent, 1849-1924; Rowe, J. W.; Voitle, C. E.; Voll, Jon A.
2293700
- Index (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to Members of the Executive Board, 1902-1905 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Folder 1 of 5. August 14 1902 - February 11 1905
- Correspondence to Members of the Executive Board, 1905-1907 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Folder 2 of 5. February 18 1905 - April 17 1907
- Correspondence to Members of the Executive Board, 1907-1908 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Folder 3 of 5. May 17 1907 - June 18 1908
- Correspondence to Members of the Executive Board, 1908-1909 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Folder 4 of 5. June 17 1908 - March 3 1909
- Correspondence to Members of the Executive Board, 1909-1910 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Folder 5 of 5. March 6 1909 - February 18 1910
- Index (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to the Officers, Members and Secretaries, 1890-1904 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  May 5 1890 - June 6 1904
- Correspondence to all Members and Officers, Minutes, 1896-1906 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  September 1896 - November 22 1906
- Correspondence to Officers and Members, AFL Booklets, 1906-1908 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  December 6 1906 - October 26 1908
- Correspondence to the Officers and Members, 1908-1910 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  November 18 1908 - March 23 1910
- Index (Box 3, Folder 1)
- D. A. Hayes Correspondence and Miscellaneous Documents, 1906-1911 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  June 15 1906 - October 31 1911
- Correspondence to Members of the Executive Board, AFL Documents, 1911-1913 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  November 10 1911 - April 26 1913
- Correspondence to Members of the Executive Board, and Miscellaneous, 1913-1915 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  April 30 1913 - June 8 1915
- Golden Anniversary Convention 1927 Booklet (Box 4, Folder 1)
  July 1927
- Report of the Committee that Represented American Flint Glass Workers' Union, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  September 1911
- Miscellaneous Glassblowers Documents and Newspaper Clippings, 1908-1912 (Box 4, Folder 3)